Guide to the John Zuccotti Papers 1956-2015 MS 3018
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Biographical and Photograph Files, 1960-2015; 2.63 Linear feet
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 1992-1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
    Includes the closing on the 320 Park Avenue property (Zuccotti then President & CEO of Olympia & York) (1992); at the opening of the World Bridge Market at the World Financial Center (1995); with Paul Reichmann and John McGillicuddy at the signing of Chemical Bank's lease at Canary Wharf (1996); and at two unidentified black tie dinner events (1995, 1996).
  - Photographs. Groups & Events, 2000s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes Zuccotti with Phil Rosen of Weil (2002); at an awards dinner (2003); and with Robert Morgenthau and others.
  - Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes letters from a possibly incomplete set of A-Z files. Correspondents and subjects include the law firm Davis, Polk, Wardwell, Sunderland & Kiendl concerning Zuccotti joining the firm; an invitation to join the Book and Gavel Society and Phi Alpha Delta legal fraternity; and an invitation to join the Waite Inn of Phi Delta Phi legal fraternity; correspondence concerning Waite Inn's financial status; arrangements for Zuccotti's internship in the office of U.S. Senator Jacob Javits; Zuccotti's requests for support in acquiring a Ford Foundation fellowship; and various certifications of character and health in connection with Zuccotti's anticipated work in Venezuela.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes documents concerning potential home purchases in northwestern New Jersey and the financial disclosure form submitted to the House of Representatives Committee on Standards of Official Conduct for year 1970.
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes letters relating to Zuccotti's position as Chair of the City Planning Commission. Includes, among others, requests for meetings from the Civil Service Technical Guild, the Board of Standards and Appeals, Tishman Realty & Construction, Brooklyn's Planning Board 13, Flushing Council of Women's Organizations, Sucsy Inner-City Developments, and others; the text of remarks by architect Max Wechsler opposing a zoning amendment in relation to nursing home construction; developer Robert V. Tishman's "A New Concept for Subsidized Housing"; Bay Ridge resident Lily Lang's opposition to the proposed construction of a high rise building (Shore Hill) by Lutheran Medical Center; Bronx resident Rev. J.J. Cronin concerning the shortage of apartments for the average New Yorker; and the program and list of attendees at Chase Manhattan Bank's Public Officials Outing at Pocantico Hills.
  - Correspondence, Congratulations (8 folders), 1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4-11)
    Includes letters of congratulations for Zuccotti's appointment as First Deputy Mayor of New York City. The correspondents include a broad range of city and state politicians, city agency staff, unions, business interests, academics, lawyers, neighborhood associations, religious figures, non-profits, and many others. Notable names include Donald Trump (folder 2), Mario Cuomo (folder 3), and Consul General of Italy Vieri Trexler (folder 5). Includes material about the activist organization Independent City in the City of New York (folder 1).
  - Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes a small number of documents dating from Zuccotti's tenure as Deputy Mayor. Among these are a transcript of WINS radio's editorial support for the appointment of Zuccotti; a copy of the 1 January 1976 edition of The Wave newspaper of Rockaway Beach with an article concerning Zuccotti installing officers of the Regular Democratic Club of the Rockaways; a press release regarding a private initiative by graphic artist Ralph Fasanella to sell posters with profits going to New York City; the resignation letter of Director of the Budget Melvin N. Lechner, and its acceptance by Mayor Beame; a letter to President-elect Jimmy Carter from Congressman Thomas L. Ashley recommending Zuccotti as Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, and an endorsement of same from Richard R. Shinn, President and Chief Executive Officer of Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, to Bert Lance, nominee for head of the Office of Management and Budget.
  - Correspondence, Congratulations (3 folders), 1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13-15)
    Includes notes of congratulations from law firms, city and state politicians, and others to Zuccotti on his departure from the Deputy Mayor position to return to private law practice in the firm of Tufo, Johnston, Zuccotti & Allegaert. The third folder includes a small number of documents from 1977 not directly related to his departure, including reflections by former City Planning Commission member Alexander D. Garvin on Zuccotti's contributions.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes letters, mostly thanks for donations and other matters, from Mayor Edward I. Koch, U.S. Senator Jacob Javits, Rabbi Morris Sherer supporting Zuccotti's efforts to save Yeshiva Chofetz Chaim, Hugh Carey's acknowledgement and thanks concerning Zuccotti's Chairmanship of the World Trade Center Task Force (1981), City Council President Carol Bellamy's thanks for Zuccotti's counsel, Edward (Ted) Kennedy, Gary Hart, and others.
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes mostly thanks for donations or other help, or forwarding contributions to Zuccotti in connection with his award from Catholic Charities. Correspondents include Edward Koch, Mario Cuomo, and Bishop of Brooklyn Francis J. Mugavero. Also a letter from developer Robert A. Rosen concerning Tufo & Zuccotti's services in connection with 48 Old Slip and several outgoing letters from Zuccotti acknowledging good wishes sent him in connection with a surgery.
  - Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    Includes letters, mostly thanks for donations, speaking appearances, and other matters, as well as other courtesies, from Edward Koch, Brooklyn Borough President Howard Golden, John V. Lindsay, and others.
  - Correspondence, 1990-2015 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes an excerpt from John V. Lindsay's remarks at the New York Leadership Conference, forwarded by Lindsay to Zuccotti (1990). Includes thanks from Governor Andrew M. Cuomo for Zuccotti's work on the Airport Advisory Panel and thanks from Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg for Zuccotti's contribution to the Republican National Convention Host Committee (2004).
  - Clippings, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, Daily News, 1973 July 29-30 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    Includes two issues of the Daily News, with headlines related to the Rockfest crowd at Watkins Glen.
  - Clippings, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, New York News Magazine Cover Article, 1976 May 9 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1980s (2 folders) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24A-24B)
  - Clippings, 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, Oversize, 1990, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 16)
    Includes the New York Times Magazine of 11 November 1990, with an advertising supplement regarding Downtown Manhattan (Zuccotti on page 8A); real estate business magazine Grid of October 2001 (Zuccotti-related article on page 20); Real Estate Weekly of 12 June 2002 (Zuccotti on page 1 and S6-7); Real Estate Weekly, 50th Anniversary Edition of August 2005 (Zuccotti in Industry Titans section, pages 1 and 22).
- Series II. Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) Project Files, 1956-1966, 1978; 1 Linear feet
  Biographical / Historical
  The Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) was founded in 1960 as an agency of the Venezuelan government. Its purpose was the large scale economic development of Venezuela's Guayana region, including the creation of a new city, Santo Tomé de Guayana (now known as Ciudad Guayana), which would serve as the area's industrial center. The region was rich in natural resources, including iron ore and gold, as well as energy sources, notably hydroelectric power, yet was sparsely settled and developed. With the creation of the CVG, a steel mill was started in 1960 and the Guri Dam was begun in 1963 on the Caroni River. A new municipal government was elected in December 1963.
  In 1961, the CVG contracted with the Joint Center for Urban Studies of MIT and Harvard for technical advisory and consulting services in all phases of the city and region development work, including economic development, urban design, and public policy requirements. The Joint Center was created in 1959 as a research organization bringing together the academic staff of both MIT and Harvard to address urban issues.
  Among the staff hired by the Joint Center to work in Venezuela on the CVG project was a new law school graduate, John Zuccotti. Zuccotti was hired to start in June 1963 with his work concluding in September 1964, with a possible extension to December 1964. Zuccotti worked with the team responsible for preparing an organizational framework for implementing the city's community service program. Specifically, Zuccotti assisted in preparing new by-laws for CVG and a charter for a subsidiary of the corporation to facilitate CVG's goals, drafting a preliminary charter for a housing foundation to administer the housing program, preparing a basic contract for "self-help" housing, and preparing legislation for the new municipal government. In his work with the CVG and Joint Center, Zuccotti was engaged with the core issues that he would be associated with for his rest of his career—land tenure, land use, housing, urban planning, and their connections to economic development.
  (The above note was based largely on documents found in the collection.)
  The series includes reports, correspondence, memos, proposals, working papers, notes, drafts, and print matter prepared by the Joint Center and/or CVG staff. Much of the material concerns proposals for an urban development corporation (corporacion de desarrollo urbano) to handle managerial matters for the CVG, the nature of the local municipal government, and the legal research, analyses and draft legislation related to those. The print matter in the series includes the decree establishing the CVG, overviews of the project, and some newsletters and annual reports of the CVG. A substantial number of the documents are in Spanish. The container list provides specific highlights of particular documents in the files.
  The series is generally organized by document type. The series opens with various reports and papers, followed by correspondence, and closes with files of rough notes and reference material. Two reports related to the CVG are found in Series III, in the Tenants Right folder (Box 5, folder 8-9).
  - Booklets. Joint Center for Urban Studies, 1964?, circa 1978 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes two copies of the booklet "Developing Venezuela's Guayana" (1964?), which provides an overview of the project, and a publicity booklet "Joint Center for Urban Studies of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard University," which provides an overview of the Center as of circa 1978. Both are in English.
  - Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG). Print Matter (3 folders), 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2-4)
    Includes booklet Guayana: Cornerstone of the Development of Venezuela (August 1963), which serves as an English language primer on the subject matter of this series. Other print matter, all in Spanish, includes CVG's Informe Anual (annual report) for 1963; the brochure "Antecedents," a "separata" of CVG's Informe Anual; and Revista Santo Tome de Guayana, published by CVG, issues for year II, numbers 2, 3, and 4 (January-August 1964).
  - "A Report to the Joint Center for Urban Studies...Concerning Some Aspects of the Projected Guayana City", 1962? (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Report by William Alonso of Harvard. Written in English.
  - "Policies for Land Tenure and Disposal (Including the Question of Plusvalia)", 1962 November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Report to CVG by William A. Doebele, Jr., Aura Mercedes Garcia-Pike, and Steven Kass. The bulk of the report is in English, but some sections are in Spanish.
  - "Governing Guayana: Roles and Responsibilities in the Public Management of Santo Tome" (draft), 1963 August (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    A CVG Staff Working Paper, prepared by the Summer Study Group in Public Administration. Written in English.
  - "A Review and Evaluation of the Original March 1962 Hypotheses on Guayana Region Development", 1963 September (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    CVG Staff Working Paper. Written in English.
  - "Physical Development Strategy for Ciudad Guayana" (revised version, draft), 1964 November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    By William Porter of the Division Estudios Planificacion e Investicacion.
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes "Work Outline for Plan for the Economic Development of the Guayana Region, 1960--70--80--2000" by Alexander Ganz (20 March 1962); notes from James N. Kise to Wilhelm V. von Moltke regarding locational characteristics of industries referred to in a report by George Perazich; notes from an interview with Dr. Moles (in Spanish); memo from Richard M. Soberman to Alexander Ganz concerning transport requirements in the Guayana region; and the Joint Center for Urban Studies job offer and description from William A. Doebele, Jr. to Zuccotti (December 1962).
  - Correspondence, 1963 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11-12)
    Includes final arrangements for Zuccotti's employment and responsibilties in Venezuela; an outline for a development strategy for Santo Tome de Guayana by Willo von Moltke; exchanges on legal points between Zuccotti and Dr. Tomas Polanco (some in Spanish); Zuccotti's summary of legal problems in establishing shopping centers; Zuccotti's summary of the project to Ronald Campbell to garner support for an article in Fortune magazine; and memos and notes on creating an Urban Development Corporation as a subsidiary of CVG to perform ongoing managerial tasks.
  - Correspondence, 1964 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13-14)
    Includes Zuccotti's analysis for a Corporacion de Desarrollo Urbano (Urban Development Corporation); exchanges between Zuccotti and Robert C. Wood of MIT and Lloyd Rodwin of the Joint Center with details on various program activities, including the creation of a housing foundation and dealing with local municipal governance matters. Some correspondence between Zuccotti and local managers is in Spanish.
  - Project Notes, circa 1964 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    Includes various notes and reference material, most undated. Includes a presupruesto (budget) for the Division de Estudios, Planification e Investigacion, Desarrollo Humano (June 1964) (in Spanish); a working draft of an agreement between the CVG and MIT for continued technical assistance (1964); Zuccotti's summary of a meeting with Bill Doebele concerning Doebele's interview with a real estate operator; a memo on "The Establishment of a 'Technical School' in Venezuela" (in English) and a memo on "Educacion Extracurricular" (in Spanish); a memo from attorney Tomas Polanco concerning the developing city (in Spanish); and various other notes and reference material.
  - A Statement of the Laws of Venezuela in Matters Affecting Business, 1956
    In English. 2nd edition, revised & enlarged. Written by Luis Loreto and Rene Lepervanche Parparcen. Published by Pan American Union.
  - Statutes Establishing the Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    Includes copies of the decree published in Gaceta Oficial de la Republica de Venezuela, the "Reglamento de Organization Interna" for CVG, and other related documents. In Spanish.
  - Urban Development Corporation Planning (2 folders), 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18-19)
    Includes various documents that appear related to the aim of creating an urban development corporation. Includes a paper "Corporacion de Desarrollo Urbano" written by Zuccotti; a draft in English of a Constituent Document creating the Caroni Housing Foundation; a draft or typescript of a decree in Spanish establishing the Fundacion de la Vivienda del Caroni (FUNVICA); a memo from Aramis Gutierrez to Hector Font concerning the activities in connection with FUNVICA; a draft "Acta Constitutiva y Estatutos de CVG Desarrollo Urbano, C.A. (CODEURRCA)"; the booklet "Administracion Municipal. Segunda Convencion Nacional de Municipalidades. Manual de Organizacion I" (1960), the "Gaceta Municipal del Distrito Federal" for 20 September 1963, and other statutory documents. Most of the documents are in Spanish.
  - Notes on Interpretations of Legal Authorities, circa 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20-21)
    Includes a "Proposicion de Ley Organica del Regimen Municipal, de Venezuela" (April 1964) and various notes and drafts that appear to be legal analyses and interpretations of Venezuelan law concerning the CVG and the juridic personality of municipalities. Most of the documents are in Spanish.
  - Reflections on Venezuelan Development (3 folders), circa 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22-24)
    Primarily includes handwritten documents that appear to be reflections in 1966 by Zuccotti on the CVG initiative in Venezuela and an outline by him of a proposed case study about the municipal government of Santo Tome de Guayana. There are also two versions of a draft paper "Legal Issues of Regional Development" by William A. Doebele, Jr. These documents appear to date from Zuccotti's time at the Department of Housing and Urban Development. See those files (Series III), specifically the folder on "Tenants' Rights," for two papers written by the CVG staff: "Planning and Administration of New Towns" (June 1963) and "Recommended Policies for Land Tenure in the City of Santo Tome de Guayana" (September 1963).
  - Address Book & Business Cards, circa 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
    Includes, among many others, Zuccotti's business card from the Joint Center for Urban Studies.
  - Miscellaneous Documents, circa 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
    Includes a list of names with associated gifts perhaps intended for them, a bilingual "Do Not Disturb" sign, and a personal budget.
- Series III. Housing & Urban Development (HUD) Files, 1966-1969; 2.33 Linear feet
  The series includes documents concerning a range of HUD initiatives of the mid-1960s. These include land use policies, urban development and housing, and efforts to alleviate urban racial tensions during the summer months. Documents include correspondence, memos, reference material, proposals, speeches and other remarks, background papers, working files, drafts of reports and other matter, press releases, and other documents. Several of the folders provide a glimpse into how HUD sought to respond to the policy pronouncements of leaders such as President Johnson and HUD Secretary Robert Weaver and to national urban issues.
  The series also includes a few files concerning particular housing projects, perhaps especially the Pruitt-Igoe housing in St. Louis, Missouri, and the Heritage Plaza site in Salem, Massachusetts. The series also includes print matter, including materials from 1968-69 concerning urban unrest and race relations.
  The series is organized by topic. Generally, the opening files in the series are on broad subjects, such as public policies or initiatives, and then move to files with a narrower focus, such as those on particular projects. The series closes with print matter.
  - Urban Land Use Policy. European Research (6 folders), circa 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-6)
    Includes specific country reports on Poland, France, Sweden, and the Netherlands; project outline; summaries; the HUD publication Industrialized Housing: A Comparative Analysis of European Experience; several booklets in German and French, particularly concerning Dusseldorf and Parlay 2 in Chesnay, Paris; and newspaper clippings in German and Italian concerning Zuccotti's visits there (December 1968).
  - Urban Land Use Policy. General (5 folders), 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7-11)
    Includes drafts of goals for metropolitan development; papers on proposed elements of a national land use policy, public and private sector roles in land use and development, and related issues; remarks by Land Development Director Dwight F. Rettie on planning; background paper on metropolitan area growth projections; and several addresses from 1966-68 by HUD Secretary Robert C. Weaver, which appear in part to be source material for a draft speech prepared by Zuccotti on the topic "Towards a National Urban Land Policy" (November 1968).
  - Neighborhood Facilities / Neighborhood Centers (5 folders), 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12-16)
    Includes documents related to HUD's response to President Lyndon B. Johnson's speech of 19 August 1966 in Syracuse, New York, in which he called on HUD to establish neighborhood service centers in "every ghetto in America." Primarily includes documents related to developing a pilot program in fourteen cities, including draft plans, program guides, inter-agency meetings, status reports, evaluations, and the like.
  - Task Force on Urban Summer Problems (2 folders), 1967 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17-18)
    Includes, among other documents, the first draft of the task force's report (October 1967) and Zuccotti's report from the Program Policy Subcommittee of the task force.
  - Summer Activities / President's Council on Youth Opportunity, 1968 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Introduction and Summary of the Report of The National Commission on Urban Problems", 1968 July 12 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    Includes the first draft of the document, prepared by Richard W. O'Neill.
  - Task Force on Home Ownership, 1967 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    Includes the contents of a binder of working papers compiled by I.P. Margulies, Chairman of the HUD Task Force on Home Ownership, and distributed to the task force members and others.
  - Urban Development Corporation Proposal (2 folders), 1966 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22-23)
    Includes "Interim Report: Study of the Feasibility of an Urban Development Corporation" (1 September 1966);, documents related to a pilot proposal for a UDC (referred to as the Santa Barbara proposal, perhaps because the Defense Research Council, based in that city, was involved in preparing it); a "Proposal for a Nationally Based Private Non-Profit Urban Development Corporation to Rehabilitate and Replace Substandard Urban Slum Dwellings"; project budgets and timelines; and other documents.
  - "Marshall Plan Speech" / Urban Development (2 folders), 1968 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Includes drafts of speeches for delivery in Cleveland titled "The Promise of the American City," other related remarks in draft and final form, other documents, and 5 booklets published by The Urban Institute.
  - "$1 Billion" / Life Insurance Industry Financing (2 folders), 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3-4)
    Includes press releases, correspondence, notes, meetings, etc. regarding the life insurance industry's commitment of $1 billion to fund urban center housing development.
  - Revenue Sharing, 1967 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    Includes mostly print matter concerning federal funding to states, with a HUD summary of a meeting of the Joint Economic Committee hearings on the subject.
  - Open Space, 1968 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes memos concerning programs and funding for open space land (including vest pocket parks), urban beautification and historic preservation (e.g., Cleveland's interest in using HUD funds to purchase the Astor Theater) in connection with metropolitan development.
  - Mass Transportation, 1968 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)